Boker tov בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's daf דף daf is, today's
daf דף daf is daf nun דף נ'. daf nun. We start
a new perek פרק, perek, the fourth perek פרק, perek, Rabbi Ishmael,
continuing to discuss issues about dealing with idols and whatnot. I mean
these I think are the fun
prakim פרקים. prakim. Just wait though, we have a lot of yayin
nesech יין נסך yayin nesech coming up. Anyway, okay, so the last
mishna משנה mishna of the previous perek פרק, perek, most of the
previous perek פרק perek dealt with when you have to assume something
was worshipped and is it forbidden in benefit and so on. This
mishna משנה mishna starts with the discussion about... and then the mishna
משנה mishna ended, the perek פרק perek ended with a discussion about
bittul ביטול bittul avodah zarah עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Alright, this mishna
משנה mishna sort of continues on both of those themes, this perek
פרק, perek, both about identifying what is an object that's worshipped, although
as a number one, as opposed to just like things like, oh
you don't know, it's an image, is it a statue, is it
aesthetic, is it really something that was worshipped, that was sort of
last perek פרק. perek. Here we deal with things that really are
directly sort of like, you know, a sort of... you'll see in
the first thing, like really seems that are in a setting of
being worshipped. And also continuing with discussions about bittul ביטול bittul and
so on. So let's take a look. It's really as I said
a continuation. Rabbi Ishmael omer אומר omer at the bottom of mem
tet amud bet מ"ט עמוד ב', mem tet amud bet, shalosh avanim
zo betzad zo Markolis שלוש אבנים זו בצד זו מרקוליס. shalosh avanim
zo betzad zo Markolis. So the classic Markolis מרקוליס Markolis in the
Gemara גמרא, Gemara, I didn't sort of do any research about what
actually,
you know, that refers to, but there was this is the classic
thing about some type of a thing that they had by the
side of the road, apparently this was I believe also,
you know, I used to travel like my... I grew up in
Maryland and when you travel from Maryland to New York, I think
it's always about an hour away from Maryland you pass this big
like church with this big statue and it's Our Lady of the
Highway. Yes, I know that. So I think Markolis מרקוליס Markolis was
sort of like the god of the highway. It was some type
of... yes, it was like a god for travelers and so on.
What? Mercury? Oh, that's interesting. Mercury?
Yes, in
Roman mythology.
Hermes is the Greek version. In the time of the Tannaim תנאים?
Tannaim?
Oh, the winged sandals?
Miercoles and once in Spanish
is
Wednesday.
Interesting. Interesting. All right, okay, you guys got a lot of source...
source... what's it called? source crowding that knowledge. Crowd sourcing. Anyway, so
apparently it would be by the side of the road and apparently
a way of worshipping is that you throw a stone at it.
You'd have these piles with three stones and you'd throw a stone
at it. And it doesn't have to be on the side of
the road. What? I know, but I think that's where they were.
Anyway, zo betzad zo Markolis זו בצד זו מרקוליס. zo betzad zo
Markolis. So he says even if they're not piled up like the
normal thing would be a triangle, two at the base and one
at the top, even if they're not piled up, they're just sort
of next to one another, you can assume sort of that that's
a Markolis מרקוליס, Markolis, maybe it collapsed. Okay, and asurot ואסורות, asurot,
and they're forbidden. Vishtayim mutarot ושתים מותרות, vishtayim mutarot, if you see
two stones, you know, I mean it's a little bizarre, any two
stones you should have a problem with? So two stones is permissible.
Vechachamim omrim וחכמים אומרים, vechachamim omrim, and the Sages say, shenirot imo
asurot v'she'eini nirot imo mutarot שנראות עמו אסורות ושאין נראות עמו מותרות.
shenirot imo asurot v'she'eini nirot imo mutarot. Okay, so if you have
stones, even if they're just two stones, and they seem connected to
a Markolis מרקוליס, Markolis, so presumably we'll see in the Gemara גמרא
Gemara there's like a standing Markolis מרקוליס Markolis and then you see
near it two stones or something of that nature, then that's a
problem. But if they don't seem connected to it, it's not a
problem. So it's not exactly clear what the parameters are, so the
Gemara גמרא Gemara jumps right into this debate. Bishlama rabanan kasavri ovdin
lishvarim בשלמא רבנן קסברי עובדין לשברים. bishlama rabanan kasavri ovdin lishvarim. So
the Rabbis presumably here have, believe that you would worship it even
if it collapsed.
Now as the Gemara גמרא Gemara is going to
say even if you normally assume that if an idol falls down
and breaks into pieces you don't continue to worship it, you think
that sort of has, the god has abandoned it or whatever, but
here the very nature of it it would be a thing of
stones and you'd throw stones at it and it would be natural
for it to collapse, so here they'll hold that even if it
collapsed you continue to worship it. So therefore what? Nirot imo de'ika
lemeimar minei nafal asurot נראות עמו דאיכא למימר מיניה נפל אסורות, nirot
imo de'ika lemeimar minei nafal asurot, so presumably you've got a you
know something that was known, either you have a standing Markolis מרקוליס
Markolis or you have a place that was a shrine of Markolis
מרקוליס Markolis and here you have some stones that are right nearby.
So therefore you can presume that this used to be a Markolis
מרקוליס, Markolis, it collapsed, and they remain forbidden.
Nirot imo de'ika lemeimar minei nafal asurot נראות עמו דאיכא למימר מיניה
נפל אסורות. nirot imo de'ika lemeimar minei nafal asurot. V'she'eini nirot imo
mutarot ושאין נראות עמו מותרות, v'she'eini nirot imo mutarot, if they're not
within that immediate region, so okay, you have some stones maybe even
if they're three stones, the Rabbis say I don't care two, three
or whatever, if it's right in the range of an existing Markolis
מרקוליס Markolis or a shrine or whatever I assume it fell from
it and it's forbidden, if it's outside that range they're just stones
on the highway, you know, I don't care how many there are.
That you understand.
When you say nirot imo שנראות עמו shenirot imo does it necessarily
have to be two, can it be one?
Yeah, presumably.
Although nirot נראות nirot is in the plural.
Correct. I'm we'll get to a little bit of that later, but
that's correct. Ella Rebbe Yishmael mai kasavar אלא רבי ישמעאל מאי קסבר?
ella Rebbe Yishmael mai kasavar? But how do you understand... so for
the Rabbis it makes sense if it's right there in
the like right near it... It's a problem, otherwise fine. But what
does Rabbi Ishmael think? He doesn't have this parameter that it's found
close to this shrine. So
אי עובדין לשברים, i ovdin leshvarim,
if he assumes that people keep on worshipping it after even after
it fell, אפילו תרתי נמי, afilu tartei nami, two should be a
problem if they're close enough to presume they're connected. אי אין עובדין
לשברים, i ein ovdin leshvarim, if people don't worship it after it
collapsed, אפילו תלת נמי לא, afilu telat nami lo, three shouldn't be
a problem if they're not you know if it's collapsed, if it's
not in its original state. So אמר רב יוסף בר יוסף אמר
רב יוחנן, Amar Rav Yosef bar Yosef amar Rav Yochanan, בדאש שנטפו
ממנו דברי הכל אסורות, bedash shenatefu mimenu divrei hakol assurot, fine. Everybody
agrees that if the thing fell from the מרקוליס Markolis it remains
forbidden. ואפילו למאן דאמר אין עובדין לשברים, ve'afilu leman de'amar ein ovdin
leshvarim, even according to the one that said yesterday you don't worship
things once they've broken, idols, הני מילי עבודת כוכבים דלאו היינו אורחיה.
hanei milei avodat kochavim delav hainu orcheih. That's a normal idol where
it's not normal to break and collapse, so you know you stop
worshipping it after it broke. אבל הכא דמעיקרא צבורי מצבר, aval hacha
deme'ikara tziburei mitzbar, here the thing naturally breaks. You throw stones towards
it, it would collapse, it's part of the way sort of it's
a natural part of how this thing is play how it plays
out. היינו אורחיה, hainu orcheih, so everybody would agree. So if a
stone fell from it, everybody agrees that it's a problem. Okay, so
what's the debate?
You don't know, okay? So כי פליגי בסתמא, ki peligi bistema, where
it's unclear. Top of נ' ע"א. nun amud alef. במקורבו
נמי דאיכא למימר מיניה נפל. bimkoravo nami de'ika lemeimar mineih nafal. Now,
Rabbi Ishmael agrees to the חכמים Chachamim is what it's saying. So
the חכמים Chachamim say we all go by if it's right in
the region. So you know what? Rabbi Ishmael says I agree with
that. I'm just going to take it one step further. Okay? במקורבו
נמי דאיכא למימר מיניה נפל, bimkoravo nami de'ika lemeimar mineih nafal, if
it's close enough that it's reasonable to assume it fell from it,
דברי הכל אסורות, divrei hakol assurot, everybody agrees it's forbidden. That's what
the חכמים Chachamim say, and Rabbi Ishmael agrees to that. כי פליגי,
ki peligi, so the חידוש chiddush of Rabbi Ishmael is even when
it's not right near it. Okay? במרוחקות, bimruchakot, it's a little bit
distant. Okay, we'll see in a minute how distant. Okay, and therefore
what Rabbi Ishmael will say is, is that I will still say
even if it's distant, if it's three, presumably three stones, you know,
were מרקוליס Markolis that collapsed. Okay, even if it's a little bit
distant or were a as we'll see a little minor מרקוליס Markolis
because he believes they would make little minor מרקוליס Markolises near a
major מרקוליס. Markolis. Okay? So therefore he's saying even though I won't
say that this stuff because it's distant fell from the major one,
three stones, now presumably it means you know I assume it means
roughly the same size stones, things that you could imagine were in
this configuration. It doesn't mean you just happen to find three pebbles
or something like that, you know. But if reasonably these could have
been a little מרקוליס, Markolis, he says then even if it didn't
fall from the major one and it's just three stones lying on
the ground, then I believe they make little מרקוליס Markolises near the
major one and that that's what this was. So that's his חידוש,
chiddush, even if it didn't fall from the major one. כי פליגי
במרוחקות. ki peligi bimruchakot. Okay. והא בצד מרקוליס קתני, veha batzad Markolis
katani, but the משנה Mishnah says if Rabbi Ishmael says if you
find three next to the מרקוליס. Markolis. So that sounds like they're
dealing with the stones right in the immediate region. So the גמרא
Gemara says מאי בצד בצד ארבע אמות דידיה, mai batzad batzad arba
amot dideih, within the four אמות. amot. Now it doesn't tell you
where the חכמים Chachamim are talking about, right? This גמרא's Gemara you
know sort of partly quantitative partly not. Okay so here's your major
מרקוליס Markolis shrine. I have no idea if they put it on
an altar but let's say they did, okay. I don't know whatever,
I don't know maybe they even had more stones. Maybe that was
the altar. Maybe that was the altar. Anyway whatever it was.
Oh I had this vision of like those trail markers.
Fine whatever.
No I'm saying you know what I'm talking about here.
We're all making it up. Okay here's your major מרקוליס, Markolis, major
I don't know if it was only three let's say minimum three.
It was a big מרקוליס, Markolis, okay. Now up to here is
your four אמות. amot. Anything within four אמות amot is considered to
be בצד. batzad. Okay but the ניראת עמו nirait imo amount is
different. The ניראת עמו... nirait imo...
Is this a dry erase?
Yeah. Okay, so the ניראת עמו nirait imo would be like right
here. Anything right here like right, and it doesn't tell you exactly
where the line is.
Gosh it's like an אמה. amah.
An אמה, amah, an אמה amah and a half, great. So okay
tell me exactly. Anything very close, everybody agrees, one, two, three, it's
a problem. Presumably it fell off of the main one. The question
is that it's not in the, it's within close enough, it's in
the general region but not close enough that you would assume it
fell off. Okay and here Rabbi Ishmael says if you find three
stones we can assume that they were originally configured as a little
mini מרקוליס Markolis nearby. And the חכמים Chachamim say no. Once it's
far enough away that I don't think it fell off, even if
it's within four אמות amot I'm not going to be concerned. Okay
so that's the debate.
And
all agree if it's after four...
And all presumably would agree that after four אמות amot it definitely
would not be a problem. It wouldn't have fallen off and it
wouldn't be a mini
מרקוליס.
Markolis. How big does an object have to be...
Yeah to be a stone that could be a מרקוליס Markolis stone.
I have no idea.
And in other words where if
if the idol was worship of a river you could still use
the river.
Yeah that we learned last פרק. perek. That's something attached to the
ground. They can't make something forbidden if it's part of the landscape.
These are movable things. Okay so... Even if it's like a boulder
it wouldn't make it... Well that the גמרא Gemara actually had that
if you remember a little bit of a question, something that's not
attached to the ground but also... Now. So בצד ארבע אמות amot,
דידי *betzad arba amot didei*, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael, סבר עושין מרקוליס
Markolis. קטן בצד מרקוליס Markolis. גדול *Rabbi Yishmael savra osin Markalis katan
betzad Markalis gadol*.
They would make little mini מרקוליס Markulis. *Markalises*. שלוש *Shalosh*, if you
find three stones,
now they're not configured as a triangle, as a little pyramid, there's
just three, but דדמיין למרקוליס *de-damyan le-Marcolis*, they reasonably could have been
configured like a מרקוליס Markulis. *Marcolis* and they look like that's what
they might have been. אסורות *Asurot*, that's forbidden even though they didn't
fall off the big one. שתים מותרות *Shtayim mutarot*, two is okay.
רבנן סברי אין עושין מרקוליס Markulis קטן בצד מרקוליס Markulis גדול *Rabbanan
savri ein osin Markalis katan betzad Markalis gadol*. No, if it didn't
fall off the big one, it's not a problem. You don't make
little מרקוליס Markulis, *Markalises*. לא שנא שלוש ולא שנא שתים *Lo shena
shalosh ve-lo shena shtayim*, it doesn't matter three or two. נראית עמו
אסורות *Niret imo asurot*, if it's right near it and could have
reasonably fallen off, it's a problem. שאין נראית עמו מותרות *She-ein niret
imo mutarot*, if not, it's not a problem. You always have to
love these debates, like, okay, there was an answer. Did they make
little mini מרקוליס Markulis. *Markalises* nearby or not? Presumably the answer is:
sometimes. So רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael *Rabbi Yishmael* sort of said, I'm
worried enough to be concerned about that, and the חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim*
say, yeah, that's an exception, we're not worried about it. Anyway, let's
take a look. אמר amar, מר *Amar mar*. So let's go back
and unpack what we just said before. It's actually interesting that this
אמר מר *amar mar* is unpacking not a Tannaitic statement, but it's
unpacking a statement of, you know, אמר רבי יוחנן *amar Rabbi Yochanan*.
I don't know, it struck me as unusual. I don't know how
often we do אמר מר *amar mar* by an Amoraic statement. Anyway,
let's unpack this statement we just had by רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*.
בידוע שנשרו ממנו דברי הכל אסורות *Be-yaduah she-nashru mimenu divrei hakol asurot*.
If you know for sure it came from it, everybody agrees it's
a problem. This is not an issue of עובדין לשברים *ovdin le-shevarim*
here, of course, you would definitely continue to worship it. ורמינהי U'Reminhu,
*U-ramini*, now I'll ask you about that. אבנים שנשרו מן המרקוליס *Avanim
she-nashru min ha-Marcolis*, here we have a ברייתא Braita: *brayta*. Stones that
fell, presumably you know for sure they fell off of it. נראית
עמו אסורות שאין נראית עמו מותרות *Niret imo asurot she-ein niret imo
mutarot*. Even those that fell, they only remain a problem if they
are sort of seen together with it. Once they've rolled far enough
away that they're no longer perceived together with it, it's not a
problem. Now what's the logic there? So רש״י Rashi *Rashi* says the
logic according to that, reading it like it's פשט *pshat*, is that
the question whether they would continue to worship it after it fell
would be a function if it would stay in the region or
not. If it were to roll away into the forest, forget it,
it's broken off, we're not going to. If it's still in the
basic zone, then we continue to worship it as part of the
configuration. So this ברייתא braita *brayta* makes it sound that even if
it fell off, they would not necessarily continue to worship it unless
it remained within the region. נראית עמו אסורות שאין נראית עמו מותרות
*Niret imo asurot she-ein niret imo mutarot*. Okay, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
*Rabbi Yishmael*
now, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael *Rabbi Yishmael* holds, אומר שלוש אסורות שתים
מותרות *omer shalosh asurot shtayim mutarot*. Three is forbidden, two are permissible,
okay, like he says in the משנה Mishnah *mishna*. So that sounds
like a very different read. That's a ברייתא braita: *brayta*, okay, but
what it adds to our משנה Mishnah: *mishna* is it says they
definitely rolled off. So it sounds from that ברייתא braita, *brayta* a
very different debate. Everybody agrees they rolled off and the question is
under what circumstances do they continue to worship it? Seen together with
it, not seen together with it, three, two, etc. Very different than
how we discussed the debate, which was questions about you're uncertain about
the facts. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to re-read the
ברייתא braita *brayta*. אמר רבא Amar Rava, *Amar Rava*, לא תימא שנשרו
*lo tima she-nashru*, don't read the ברייתא braita. *brayta* that they definitely
fell off. אלא אימא שנמצאו *ela eima she-nimtzu*, it means that they
are nearby, you're concerned that they fell off. It doesn't mean they
literally fell off. Which I think is probably a reasonable read. שנשרו
*She-nashru* means like we're concerned they were נשרו *nashru*. It doesn't mean
that we know for sure they were נשרו *nashru*. That's how רבא
Rava, *Rava* reads it. Okay, and therefore, so now we're back to
our משנה Mishnah *mishna*. So the חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim* say, if it's
right nearby, it's a problem because you assume they fell off. Further
away, it's not. And רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael *Rabbi Yishmael* says the
way we're reading it, even not right nearby, שלוש *shalosh* within ארבע
אמות amot? *arba amot* remains a problem. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says like this: וסבר רבי ישמעאל שתים מותרות *ve-savar Rabbi
Yishmael shtayim mutarot*, now does רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* really hold that
two are permissible if they're not right nearby? והתניא Vehatanya, *Ve-hatanya*, we
taught in a ברייתא braita, *brayta*, רבי ישמעאל אומר שתים בתפיסה לו
אסורות *Rabbi Yishmael omer shtayim bitfisa lo asurot*. Two, if they're in
one like grabbing, like one, now that's a different language we've had.
Notice we've had two languages, right? This is, this language here was
בצד *betzad*. Up to ארבע אמות amot. *arba amot*
is
considered בצד *betzad*. Within whatever we don't know how much this region
is, this is considered to be נראית עמו *niret imo*. Okay, very
precise sort of definitions here. And now we're calling something else תפיסה
אחת tfisa achat *tfisa achat*, one like unit, one grabbing. Okay,
and we'll see what that means in a minute in the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*. It's a slightly different definition. Okay, so here we have
the following. והתניא *Ve-hatanya*, oh where where? והתניא *Ve-hatanya*, רבי ישמעאל אומר
שתים בתפיסה לו *Rabbi Yishmael omer shtayim bitfisa lo*, if there are
two and they're in the same sort of unit with it, אסורות
*asurot*, then even two is going to be a problem. שלוש *Shalosh*,
and three, אפילו מרוחקות אסורות *afilu meruchakot asurot*, is a problem even
if they're distant. So this is another problem. We were assuming שלוש
*shalosh* is only a problem within ארבע אמות amot *arba amot*. Here
he sounds like שלוש *shalosh* is a problem very far away.
Yes. But they're not configured like a pyramid and how far away
is far away? So we now have a whole different thing: what
is תפיסה אחת, tfisa achat how far away is three? It's a
completely... it all gets very confused. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אמר רבא, לא קשיא. lo kashya. Oh, that's not a problem.
כאן בתפיסה אחת כאן בשתי תפיסות. Kan bitfisa achat kan bishte tfisot.
It's a question whether it's in one unit or multiple units. What
does that mean? והיכי דמי? Veheichi dami? What's the case? דאיכא גובה
ביני וביני. De'ika govah beini uveini. Okay, that there would be a
little type of a mound of dirt between them. So תפיסה אחת
tfisa achat means if they're not separated with a little mound of
dirt. Okay, we'll draw on this side. If there's a little mound
of dirt here, okay, and then you have stones over here, right?
Then that's a problem because... that's not a problem because clearly they're
not, even if they're within close proximity. It's sort of like, you
know, the מגילה, Megillah, like I say, near Sima, not near Sima.
How physically close, if there's something that divides them, then you're not
concerned that that's going to be some type of מרקוליס. Markulis Why?
Because it wouldn't have rolled away. It wouldn't have rolled off. It
would have hit the mound. And the idea that they make a
little mini one, if no, they're not configured like a pyramid, they're
just three stones. The idea they make a mini one near a
big one is also only if they're somehow seen together. If they're
divided, not. Now, we still have to figure out what this means
קרוב ומרוחק. karov umeruchak. But before I get to that, why is
it there anyway? I don't know, you gotta go to the bathroom,
you use it to wipe yourself, you want to use it as
a paperweight, whatever.
So, so, okay, so I should say by the way this idea
of תפיסה אחת is also relevant because the ראשונים Rishonim borrowed from
this גמרא Gemara to a discussion in חולין Chullin that talks about
eating meat and milk at the same table. You're not allowed to
eat meat next to somebody who's eating milk and whatever, vice versa
obviously, because you might accidentally, if you know, just take some, take
something. Because since it's all היתר, heter, it's actually you're allowed to
eat next to somebody eating חזיר, chazir, but you can't eat next
to somebody eating milk because you know to keep away from חזיר,
chazir, milk you don't need to keep away from. So, you know,
so Michael's there eating cheese and I'm here eating my salami sandwich
and I say, "Oh, can I have some? That looks like that
would go good on my salami sandwich," and I forget. Or even
if I don't exactly do that, I finished eating my salami sandwich
and there's a nice-looking, like, I you know, chocolate bar and I
just, Michael's my friend, I just take a little piece of chocolate.
So we can't eat it next to each other. But the גמרא
Gemara says that's only like בתפיסה אחת. bitfisa achat. If it's שתי
תפיסות, shte tfisot, it's allowed. So what's תפיסה אחת and שתי תפיסות?
shte tfisot? So they borrow from this גמרא Gemara and they say,
"Well, if I've got, let's say, some type of a barrier between
us," like actually like a physical, I don't know, like a like
a vase or something, I'm not about to go do it. And
then the question becomes let's say it's not a physical barrier but
it's a היכר. heker. It's a... on two ends of the table
also, but it's a היכר. heker. You're eating on a on a
placemat and I'm not eating on a placemat. Anyway, so I just
wanted to point out that this גמרא Gemara actually is borrowed for
that discussion. Now, back to this. Okay, so what does this mean
now? So now what we have him saying is if it's בתפיסה
אחת, bitfisa achat, okay, so back to this, he says two בתפיסה
אחת bitfisa achat is a problem. So what is the case of...
hold on, let me get this back again. ורמינהו ורבי ישמעאל אומר
שתיים בתפיסה לו אסורות. Veraminhu VeRabbi Yishmael omer shtayim bitfisa lo asurot.
Two nearby is a problem. So what does that mean? Is that
talking within the four אמות, amot, within these two אמות? Amot So
there's a whole debate of רש''י Rashi תוספות. Tosafot. I'm sorry, I
just have to check, remind myself. Let me just double check how
תוספות Tosafot explains it because תוספות Tosafot was I think a little
clearer than רש''י. Rashi.
One minute. וכאן היה
לפרש לעולם כך יסבור דבתוך ארבע.
Vechan haya
lefaresh le'olam kach yisbor debetoch arba. If you look at תוספות Tosafot
four lines before the lines get wide, he says, דלעולם כך יסברא
דבתוך ארבע אמות נמי יש שאין נראות, Dele'olam kach yasbra debetoch arba
amot nami yesh she'ein nirot, כי דקרי ליה מרוחקות בתוך ארבע אמות.
ki dekari lei meruchakot betoch arba amot. והכי פירושו כאן בתפיסה אחת
דליכא גובה ובתוך ארבע אמות, Ve'hachi peirusho kan bitfisa achat delika govah
uvetoch arba amot,
אף על גב שאין נראות קאמר רבי
ישמעאל דאפילו שתיים אסורות. af al gav she'ein
nirot ka'amar Rabbi
Yishmael deafilu shtayim asurot. ואפשר לומר דמרקוליס קטן הן כיון שהם בתוך
ארבע אמות, Ve'efshar lomar demarkolis katan hen keivan shehem betoch arba amot,
ודווקא שתיים אבל אחת מותרות בין נראות בין אי נראות... vedavka shtayim
aval achat mutarot bein nirot bein i nirot... ומרקוליס
גדול לא עבדי. umarkolis gadol lo avdi. והדר קאמר להלן בשתיים מותרות
מאי בבי תפיסה. Vehadar ka'amar lehalan bishtayim mutarot mai bevei tfisa. Okay.
So basically what it's saying is is that he actually is saying
that if it is, everything has to take place according to תוספות
Tosafot within four אמות. Amot More than four אמות is is never
a problem. And within four אמות, if there's no barrier between them,
אין הכי נמי, ein hachi nami, even two would be a problem.
But if there is a barrier between them, then only three are
going to be a problem. All right, it gets very confusing how
you factor all these things together. But the bottom line is we're
still basically committing to our basic understanding. For the חכמים only very
close we say it fell off. For רבי ישמעאל, he believes that
there are cases where even if it's far enough away that it
didn't fall off, they would still make a mini מרקוליס. Markulis. to
worship. So the basic idea is okay under what circumstances? So one
scenario is it's within four אמות and there are, the way תוספות
Tosafot reads it, even two within four. We have to say maybe
this came from a mini מרקוליס. Markulis? If there's a barrier between
them and it's within four אמות then only three. Okay, so different
ways of configuring when we're concerned that this is a mini מרקוליס.
Markulis
All right, don't worry, it'll be on the test. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara. says like this. Okay, now ומרקוליס כי האי גוונא
מי הוה? UMarkulis kehai gavna mi havae? Now is there really, do
they really make a מרקוליס Markulis. like this? You know, like a
mini מרקוליס Markulis. near a big one? ומרקוליס כי האי גוונא מי
הוה? UMarkulis kehai gavna mi havae? והתניא, we taught in a ברייתא:
braita אלו הן אבני בית קוליס. Elu hen avnei beit Kulis. And
now it is מרקוליס, Markulis Mister Kulis, like מרחשון. Marcheshvan. Actually, it
doesn't work if it comes from the word, what do you say,
Mercury? That's Greek. What? Greek? Greek. I know, but I understand that,
but I'm saying the way they were able to drop the word
'Mar' and get to 'Kulis' seems, anyway, if it comes from Mercury,
obviously it's not the real word. Anyway, I know מרחשון Marcheshvan does
not mean Mister Cheshvan or bitter Cheshvan. Okay, אלו הן אבני בית
קוליס, Elu hen avnei beit Kulis, אחת מכאן ואחת מכאן ואחת על
גביהן. achat mikan veachat mikan veachat al gabeihen. Okay, so what do
you mean? We just said now if it's two and it's right
in the region, right, we said here now according to רבי ישמעאל
if it's two, if there's no barrier, then maybe even two would
be part of a mini מרקוליס. Markulis, So one minute, but we
know that a מרקוליס Markulis needs three. So how could רבי ישמעאל
have two? Once it's no, we said it didn't fall off and
it's, you know, it's not right nearby, so there's no barrier, we're
going to be concerned about two as a mini מרקוליס. Markulis. Since
when is two a מרקוליס? Markolis
So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבא כי תניא ההיא בעיקר מרקוליס.
Amar Rava ki tanya hahi beikar Markulis. Yeah, the primary מרקוליס Markolis
is three, but if you're, but when you're making a mini one
nearby, then you, two might even be enough. And that's why under
some circumstances רבי ישמעאל is concerned with two. Okay so again, the
חכמים are only concerned about very close that it rolled off and
then the number doesn't matter, and רבי ישמעאל is saying even if
it's not very close, if it's nearby enough with or without a
barrier depending on the circumstances, two or three could be a problem.
Fine. בינאי מלכא חרוב. Beyannai malka charuv.
Now the house of the king Yannai was destroyed. I mean, you
know, after he had, you know, died or whatever, after a while
the palace got destroyed. אתו עובדי כוכבים ואוקימו ביה מרקוליס. Atu ovdei
kochavim veokimu bei Markulis.
So the non-Jews came and with the rubble of the house they
made a מרקוליס. Markolis, אתו עובדי כוכבים אחריני דלא פלחו למרקוליס. Atu
ovdei kochavim acharinei dela palchu leMarkulis.
Other non-Jews came who didn't worship מרקוליס. Markolis, שקלינהו וחיפו בהן דרכים
וסטראות. Shaklinhu vechipu bahen drachim vesitraot.
And they used it to pave, you know, roads and highways. Okay,
so they took these things that had been מרקוליס Markolis, stones and
paved roads and highways. And now it's a good question: can we
travel on the road? Why not? It would seem like a clear
act of ביטול. Bitul. Okay, but let's take a look. איכא רבנן
דפרשי, Ika rabanan deparshi, there were some rabbis that held back and
wouldn't go on those roads. ואיכא רבנן דלא פרשי, Veika rabanan dela
parshi, and some did not hold back. אמר רבי יוחנן בנן של
קדושים מהלך עליהן. Amar Rabbi Yochanan bnan shel kedoshim mahalekh aleihen.
Even the son of the holy ones walked on them. ואנן נפרוש?
Veanan nifrosh? And we think we're so frum, we're not going to
go? So מאן ניהו בנן של קדושים? Man nihu bnan shel kedoshim?
Who is this son of the holy ones, or the sons of
the holy ones? רבי מנחם ברבי סימאי. Rabbi Menachem beRabbi Simai. ומאי
קרו ליה בנן של קדושים? Umai karu leh bnan shel kedoshim?
Why was he given this name? דאפילו בצורתא דזוזא לא מסתכל. Deafillu
betzurta dzuza lo mistakel.
He was so frum that he would not look at the money,
you know, money has, we have pictures of presidents, they would have
the pictures of the Caesars or whatever, these would be treated as
gods. He didn't want to look at any image that anybody related
to as a god, even though nobody worshipped, I mean, we could
say we all worship money nowadays, but anyway, nobody worshipped it like
that. Okay, but I don't want to look at something that other
people treat that image as a god. He was so frum about
images and he had no problem going on the roads. Who do
we think we are not to go on the roads?
What's the halakhic issue at stake here? Remember, because we actually say
that a non-Jew could be מבטל Mevatel an עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah
of a different non-Jew, it doesn't have to be your עבודה זרה.
Avodah Zarah. So מאי טעמא דמאן דפריש? Mai taama deman deparish? What's
the reason of the one who separated? סבר לה כי הא דאמר
רב גידל אמר רבי חייא בר יוסף אמר רב: Savar lah ki
ha deamar Rav Gidel amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Yosef amar Rav: מניין
לתקרובת עבודה זרה שאין לה ביטלה עולמית? Minayin letikrovet avodah zarah she'ein
lah bittalah olamit? Sure,
it's true that destroying this little מרקוליס, Markolis deconstructing it, you know,
it's not enough just to like move it or to sell it
or to whatever use it. You have to do something to like
physically change it. But if the מרקוליס Markolis, is created as a
little pyramid and you deconstruct it, that's ביטול, Bitul, okay, even though
you didn't change each individual stone, you took apart the מרקוליס. That's
ביטול. Bitul. But he says, here's the irony. The irony is that
while you could be מבטל Mevatel an עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, you
can't be מבטל Mevatel a תקרובת עבודה זרה, Tikrovet Avodah Zarah, something
that was offered to עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. I have to tell
you, I still haven't cracked this pot. why תקרובת עבודה זרה tikroves
avodah zarah is stricter. We had it earlier, a תקרובת עבודה זרה
tikroves avodah zarah is מטמא metamei like a מת, meis, like a
dead body, even under the same roof, and so on. An actual
עבודה זרה avodah zarah is only מטמא metamei like a שרץ. sheretz.
Because the stones are a base, maybe, upon which the תקרובת tikroves
is brought. תקרובת tikroves is the object.
No, I do understand,
I do
understand, I do understand, we'll get in a minute why this is
תקרובת tikroves or עבודה זרה avodah zarah itself. I'm just saying I
don't the law, the הלכה halacha that we give greater weight and
severity to something that was offered to an idol than to the
idol. If I go ahead and I slaughter an animal to Zeus,
this animal has the טומאה tuma like a like a corpse, like
a מת, meis, like a human corpse, whereas the Zeus statue only
has טומאה tuma like a שרץ. sheretz. If I go ahead and
afterwards, I'm a non-Jew, I cut off the nose of Zeus, the
statue is permissible. If I go ahead and I disgrace this the
meat that I just slaughtered, it remains forbidden. תקרובת tikroves is weightier
טומאה tuma and not changeable status as opposed to the עבודה זרה
avodah zarah itself. Now maybe that had to do with some parts
of their beliefs. You know, if they believe that an עבודה זרה
avodah zarah that their god could somehow inhabit the statue and then
the god could leave the statue and inhabit something else, and actually
I mentioned before, you know in these cultures they did have the
way of like desanctifying, you know, a process of of, you know,
transforming the statue back to being non-sanctified and having the god would
depart and he'd re-instantiate
himself in some other statue. So maybe if they themselves believed that
the status was less permanent, that's different than somehow the offering that
was brought. But one way or another, that's the הלכה. halacha. תקרובת
tikroves is weightier.
Yeah, תקרובת tikroves is active
while
the statue is static.
Yeah, so
you made the statue, you worship the statue.
No, the
the תקרובת tikroves is the object.
I understand. I don't understand why building a statue and bowing down
to it is less is less serious than I take a piece
of meat and I lay it in front of the statue, this
piece of meat has weightier status. It's not doing anything. All right,
maybe. Anyway, for one reason or another, תקרובת tikroves is weightier. So
the the point is like this. The מרקוליס was both. I mean
it wasn't both, but it was confusing what was what. You had
a little pyramid of stones and the way you would worship is
you take stones and you throw it at it. So now you
have all these stones nearby. Which ones of them are תקרובת tikroves
and which ones of them are עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? So those
that wouldn't use it wouldn't use it because they would be concerned
that the stones would be תקרובת tikroves and you can't be מבטל
mevatel תקרובת. tikroves. Okay, so let's take a look, which seems like
a reasonable concern. So let's take a look. מאי טעמא דמאן דפריש,
mai ta'ama d'man d'parish, סבר לה כי הא דאמר רב גידל אמר
רב חייא בר יוסף אמר רב, savar lah keha d'amar Rav Gidel
amar Rav Chiyya bar Yosef amar Rav, מנין לתקרובת עבודת כוכבים שאין
לה ביטול לעולמים. minayin l'tikroves avodat kochavim she'ein lah bittul le'olamim. How
do I know that an actual thing that was offered to an
idol, now again, distinct from תשמיש tashmish and נוי, noy, things that
serve the עבודה זרה avodah zarah or adorn it, do have ביטול.
bittul. The only thing that doesn't have ביטול bittul is תקרובת, tikroves,
an offering. How do I know it has no ביטול? bittul? שנאמר
ויצמדו לבעל פעור ויאכלו זבחי מתים. shene'emar v'yitzmadu l'ba'al pe'or vayochlu zivchei
meisim. Once again with this offering of the dead. מה מת אין
לו ביטול לעולמים, mah meis ein lo bittul le'olamim, the same way
a dead body never changes its status, אף תקרובת עבודת כוכבים אין
לה ביטול לעולמים. af tikroves avodat kochavim ein lah bittul le'olamim. Okay.
And it's similar
the one who, what do you call, similar the offering. Now that
seems like a very good point. If we all agreed to that
law and a lot of the stones were thrown at it in
acts of תקרובת, tikroves,
so we shouldn't use the stones, you know, even if they underwent
ביטול. bittul. ומאן דלא פריש, u-man d'lo parish, so the one who
didn't worship it, who did excuse me, didn't prevent themselves, the people
who did use the roads, אמר, they would say, בעינא כעין פנים
וליכא. be'ina ke-ein panim v'leka. No, no, no. This is not an
actual תקרובת tikroves because it's not enough like how worship not worship
how offerings were done in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Now what
makes this different from the way offerings were done in the בית
המקדש? Beis HaMikdash? רש"י Rashi says, well, you don't offer stones in
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, so he focuses on the object. And
you know, if something is like a food, you know, edible, those
are the normal things that are offered to God or the gods,
stones are not, so it doesn't have a status of תקרובת tikroves
because it's not enough like how we do things. That's basically what
רש"י Rashi says.
A chicken would be because it's food even though we don't offer
chickens in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
Exactly. תוספות Tosafot says it has to do with the way in
which it's done. We don't throw things, you know, we present them.
Well, the גמרא Gemara is going to get to this because of
some. Now this becomes a great practical question in תוספות Tosafot because
I always love these תוספותים Tosafotim they get to the they get
to the practical issue. So if you take a look at, turn
the דף daf here, it's in the middle of this big תוספות
Tosafot on the other side of the דף daf where תוספות Tosafot
says like this, he discusses his practical application of this. He says
like this, he
says right from the top. He says,
oh actually maybe it's the last line at the bottom. I'm sorry,
the last line at the bottom. He says like this on נ
עמוד א, nun amud alef, two lines from the bottom. ושמעינן מהכא,
v'shaminun mehacha, we hear from this discussion דהני נרות של שעוה שמביאין
דורון לעבודת כוכבים מדליקים בפניהם, dahani neiros shel sha'ava shemevi'im doron la'avodat
kochavim madlikim bifneihem, so you have these candles that are brought in
the church and they're put in front of the statues and they're
lit... So is that a type of a תקרובת tikrovet. *tikroves*? Okay.
And what happens? ומשכבן הכומר *u-mishe-kibban ha-komer*,
and after the priest extinguishes the candles, מוכרם ונותנם לישראל *mochram u-nosnam
le-Yisrael*. He gives them or sells them to a Jew. Can we
be in the business of repurposing church candles? Is it a תקרובת
tikrovet, *tikroves*, and a תקרובת tikrovet *tikroves* wouldn't have ביטול bitul *bittul*?
So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* says, מותר בהנאה *mutar behana'ah*. It's permissible. ממה
נפשך *miman nafshach*, either way. אי תקרובת tikrovet עבודת כוכבים הוי *ei
tikroves avodas kochavim havei*, if it was a תקרובת tikrovet, *tikroves*, אפילו
ביטול bitul לא צריך *afilu bittul lo tzarich*, ומותר בלא ביטול bitul.
*u-mutar belo bittul*. Now you wouldn't even need ביטול *bittul*. Why? Because
it means if it was meant as a תקרובת tikrovet. *tikroves*, it
wouldn't even be a problem because it wouldn't halachically be a תקרובת
tikrovet *tikroves*. Why wouldn't it? דלא דמי לתקרובת מזבח *de-lo dami le-tikroves
mizbe'ach*, because it's not a food and therefore if it was meant
only as a תקרובת tikrovet, *tikroves*, it doesn't even, then it doesn't
satisfy, it doesn't qualify as a תקרובת tikrovet *tikroves* and it's not
even a problem to begin with. ובתיקרובת שאינו כעין פנים k'ein pnim.
לא בעי ביטול *u-vitikroves she-eino ke-ein p'nim lo ba-ei bittul*. So if
it doesn't satisfy the idea of a תקרובת tikrovet, *tikroves* like we
do in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*, it doesn't get
any status. It goes from being the worst to being nothing if
you don't qualify as like it was done in the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash*. ואי נוי של עבודת כוכבים היו *ve-ei noy
shel avodas kochavim hayu*, like it's a good question: do you look
at those candles as an offering or do you look at them
as an adornment? So he says, okay, if we consider it, so
if it's an offering, it doesn't even halachically qualify, it's not the
right type, it doesn't halachically fit and it's totally מותר *mutar*. If
it's an adornment, ולנוי מדליקין אותן *u-lenoy madlikin
osan*, then שייך לו ביטול עבודת כוכבים עצמה *shayich lo bittul avodas
kochavim atzmah*. And when he extinguishes it, ומכל מקום מכיוון שכיבן הכומר
*u-mikol makom mikivan she-kibban ha-komer*, so once he extinguishes it, אין לך
ביטול גדול מזה *ein lach bittul gadol mizeh*, זה ביטול *ze bittul*,
דשוב אינו רוצה להדליקן לפני עבודת כוכבים אלא להנות מהן *de-shuv eino
rotzeh le-hadlikan lifnei avodas kochavim ella le-hanos me-hen*, ולצרכנו לן *u-letzarchenu lan*,
okay. And then so he goes on and on with a great
תוספות *Tosafos*, he discusses all the different types of trade the Jews
did with church items and he goes figuring out: is this נוי
*noy*? Is it תקרובת tikrovet, *tikroves*? How about selling the clothes that
the priests would wear? Well, that's not נוי *noy* of the idol,
of the object, that's נוי *noy* for the priest and you know,
so he goes through like all, jumps through all the various hoops.
So it's a great תוספות *Tosafos* figuring out those realities. Okay, so
back to the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, that's the issue. All right, so
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: before we turn the
דף daf *daf*, though, I do want to point out one other
תוספות *Tosafos* about אבני בית קוליס *avnei beis Kolis*. תוספות *Tosafos* says,
הקשה רבינו תם *hikshah Rabbeinu Tam*, היך מזכירין שמה כיוון שאינה כתובה
בתורה *heich maskirin shemah keivan she-eina kesuvah ba-Torah*. We have a problem
about mentioning names of עבודה זרה avoda zara *avodah zarah*, right? So
if קוליס *Kolis* was really the name, how do we say the
name? ואמר רבינו תם *ve-omar Rabbeinu Tam*, דקילוס לשון שבח שמה *de-kilus
lashon shevach shemah*, that, right, לקלס *lekales*.
So again, he's doing a Hebrew etymology of a Greek word.
And the Hebrew comes from the Greek.
Okay, okay, maybe. Anyway, so he says originally the word was
קילוס *kilus* which meant praise, וחכמים תיקנו אותו קוליס לשון לעג וקלס
*ve-chachamim tiknu oso Kolis lashon lag va-keles*,
and we made a little change to make it mean like a
mockery. So this I wanted you to see this because that we
just learned that גמרא *Gemara* recently about how you take names of
עבודה זרה avoda zara *avodah zarah* and you make a little change
to make it mean something, you know, derogatory rather than something positive.
So תוספות *Tosafos* claims, I don't know if he's correct, but he
claims that's what we did with this word מרקוליס *Markolis* as well.
We took a positive sounding name and made it a negative one.
Okay, but back to the גמרא *Gemara*. So the גמרא *Gemara*'s argument
is that this doesn't qualify as an actual תקרובת tikrovet, *tikroves* and
therefore it doesn't even need ביטול *bittul*. Maybe if it needs ביטול
*bittul* it's because it was both a תקרובת tikrovet? *tikroves* and then
maybe after you threw it, maybe it also became an object of
worship as well. So these things that were thrown could have been
both תקרובת tikrovat *tikroves* and עבודה זרה avoda zara, *avodah zarah*. But
as עבודה זרה avoda zara *avodah zarah* it was ביטול *bittul*. They
used the stones to pave the roads. That's not a problem. The
question was: does it also, is it also in the category of
תקרובת tikrovat? *tikroves*? And the גמרא *Gemara*'s answer is no, because it's
not like they would do in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, which
there's a question: does it mean the object is not a food
type of an object, or does it also mean the act is
not an act of offering that would be done in the בית
המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*? Okay, but one way or another, it's not a
תקרובת *tikroves* and it's not a problem. So now let's continue in
the גמרא *Gemara*. אמר רב יוסף בר אבא amar Rav Yosef bar
Abba: איקלע רבא בר ירמיה Bar Yirmeya, לאתראן *Amar Rav Yosef bar
Abba ikla Rava bar Yirmiyah le-asran*. Rava bar Yirmiyah came by our
place and ואתא veata ואייתי מתניתא בידיה veaysei matnita bidei, *ve-asa ve-aisi
masnisa
biyadei*, and he brought with him a ברייתא braita? *braisa*. עובד כוכבים
שהביא אבנים מן המרקוליס *Oved kochavim sheheivi avanim min ha-Markolis*, if a
non-Jew brought rocks from the מרקוליס *Markolis* וחיפה בהן דרכים וסרטיאות *ve-chippa
bahen derachim vesartiyot*, and he used it to pave, you know, roads
and highways.
I'm assuming, how does it translate סרטיאות *sartiyot*? Highways or theaters? Theaters?
Okay, that's interesting. I was thinking that it was a play on
the word highways. Yeah, I think so, because I think it's the
word איסטרטיא *stratiya* is a highway, I thought סרטיאות *sartiyot*, anyway, one
or the other. Okay, מותרות *mutaros*. It's permissible, okay, because that was
a ביטול *bittul* of the עבודה זרה avoda zara *avodah zarah* status
of it that the non-Jew did. Non-Jews can be מבטל mevatel *mevattel*
עבודה זרה avoda zara. *avodah zarah*. And again, according to this, it
never had a status of תקרובת *tikroves*. ישראל שהביא אבנים מן המרקוליס
וחיפה בהן דרכים וסרטיאות *Yisrael sheheivi avanim min ha-Markolis ve-chippa bahen derachim
vesartiyot*, but if a Jew did it, אסורות *asuros*. They're forbidden because
a Jew can't be מבטל mevatel. *mevattel* the עבודה זרה avoda zara?
*avodah zarah* status. לית, so this was the ברייתא Baraita he brought,
and then he said, ולית נגר ולא בר נגר דיפרקינה, veleit nagar
velo bar nagar d'yafarkina,
but we have no carpenter or son of carpenter, which is a
main like we have no wise person who can like, you know,
unpack that, who can explain that. Why should it be that if
a גוי goy does it, it's okay, and a Jew does it,
it's not okay? Now the question is like, huh? That's obvious. I
mean, from the very last, you know, anybody who's been learning for
the last two weeks knows that a non-Jew can be מבטל mevatel
עבודה זרה avoda zara and a Jew cannot. But maybe the one
who felt that he can't explain it assumed that this was a
תקרובת. And if it's a תקרובת, like maybe didn't understand that it
was an עבודה avoda זרה itself. Maybe he felt like, make up
your mind, either it's תקרובת and then even a non-Jew can't make
it permissible, or it's not a תקרובת and then it was never
forbidden. What is this middle status that it requires a non-Jew to
make it permissible? And the answer is, it's not a תקרובת, but
it actually is itself worshipped, it's itself an עבודה avoda זרה, even
after you throw the stone, the stone itself becomes an object of
worship, right? And that's why it needs a non-Jew to be מבטל.
mevatel But you understand the normal thing to say if you throw
stones at it is that the stones thrown are תקרובת. And then
the answer is like, okay, so either nobody can be מבטל mevatel
it, including a non-Jew, or you don't need anybody to be מבטל
mevatel? it if you say that it's not a real תקרובת because
it's not כעין פנים. k'ein panim. What's the middle status? What's the
logic? And the answer is, it's not only a תקרובת, it's also
an עבודה avoda זרה itself. Okay, but anyway, he said, I he
said there's nobody who can explain this. So, אמר רב ששת amar
Rav Sheshet so said רב ששת: Rav Sheshet: אנא לא נגר אנא
ולא בר נגר אנא, ana lo nagar ana velo bar nagar ana,
I'm not a carpenter and I'm not the son of a carpenter,
but ופרקינה לה, veparkina la, but I can explain it. מאי קשיא
ליה? mai kashya lei? מאי קשיא ליה, mai kashya lei, what's bothering
him? דרב גידל. deRav Giddal. בעינא כעין פנים וליכא. beina k'ein panim
velika. So what's bothering him? What's bothering him is רב גידל's Rav
Giddal rule that nobody should be allowed to be מבטל mevatel. it
because it's תקרובת עבודה זרה. tikrovet avoda zara. So how could anybody
be מבטל? But the answer is, it's not תקרובת עבודה זרה tikrovet
avoda zara because it's not כעין פנים. k'ein panim It's a rock,
it's thrown, and that's why it's not a תקרובת and that's why
it can have ביטול and that's why non-Jews can be מבטל. Okay.
Wait, then it becomes part of the landscape again?
No, presumably it would stay right in that region and so would
be used for roads.
What? Yeah. So what's your question?
You see, like a river, something that's part of the landscape?
Yeah, but you can't make something that's מחובר, mechubar, you can't make
it forbidden. If something was forbidden and you're מחובר- mechubar and then
you attach it to the ground, it doesn't lose its status. Yeah.
So what did you say נגר nagar was?
I thought it meant carpenter. Why, how do they translate? נגר nagar
is carpenter, literally. No, it's a metaphor for a scholar, literally it's
a carpenter.
He's an Aramaic and Hebrew carpenter thing.
Yeah, it's probably like יכניה Yechania where he took the חרש והמסגר
choresh vehamasger and he like, yeah, it's a metaphor, like you know,
you you know, you cut things up, you reconstruct them, it's like,
you know, yeah.
Point out the irony of that metaphor in this גמרא. Right.
Because who
else was a carpenter?
Jesus? I don't know. But are we talking why, I don't know
why we should be assuming that context here, but okay. I mean
we are talking about like Roman paganism in this context. All right,
anyway. All right, in the greater... oh but you mean also the
son of a carpenter. Okay, anyway. Okay, fine. So your what bothered
you is that ביטול shouldn't happen at all because it's תקרובת, and
the answer is it's not תקרובת, that's halakhic תקרובת, and that's why
it can have ביטול. Okay. Now, now because we have this metaphor
about
a carpenter and son of a carpenter and difficulty a difficult teaching,
we're going to digress for the rest of the דף about this.
Okay? So, אמר רב יוסף בר אבא: איקלע רבה בר ירמיה לאתראן,
ikla Rabba bar Yirmiya le'asran, רבה בר ירמיה Rabba bar Yirmiya came
to our place, ואתא veata, is it the same one before? רבה
בר ירמיה. Rabba bar Yirmiya. Okay. ואתא, and he came, ואייתי מתניתא
בידיה, and he brought the following ברייתא: Baraita מתלין ומסימין בשביעית, matlin
umasimim bishvi'is, you can de-worm trees and do מסימין, masimim, which רש״י
Rashi basically says is a way of like attaching bark to trees
to keep them sturdy by use dung to attach bark to trees.
You can do that on שמיטה. Shmita. ואין מתלין ומסימין במועד, ve'ein
matlin umasimim bemo'ed, and you can't do it though on חול המועד.
Chol HaMoed. כאן וכאן אין מגזמין, kan vekan ein megazmin, in neither
case can you prune the tree, neither on שמיטה Shmita or חול
המועד. Chol HaMoed. וסכין שמן לגזום, vesachin shemen legazum, but if you
have a tree that's already been pruned, you can put oil on
the place of the cut, בין במועד בין בשביעית, bein bemo'ed bein
bishvi'is, whether it's on חול המועד Chol HaMoed or on שמיטה. Shmita.
That was the ברייתא, Baraita and presumably this is the way that
he ended the ברייתא braita by saying, commenting, ולית נגר ולא בר
נגר דיפרקינה, veleit nagar velo bar nagar d'yafarkina, but I don't there's
no carpenter or the son of carpenter who can explain this ברייתא.
אמר רבינא, amar Ravina, so said רבינא: Ravina: אנא לא נגר אנא
ולא בר נגר אנא, ana lo nagar ana velo bar nagar ana,
I'm not the carpenter or son of a carpenter, ומפרקינא לה, umfarkina
la, and I can explain it. Okay, now we have to understand
what bothered you about this ברייתא, what was difficult? The previous ברייתא
the difficulty was, since when can you allow a תקרובת? What's bothers
what bothers you with this ברייתא? מאי קא קשיא ליה, mai kakashya
lei, what bothers it? אילימא מועד אשביעית קא קשיא ליה, ileima mo'ed
ashvi'is kakashya lei, maybe you just don't understand why should things be
forbidden on חול המועד Chol HaMoed and permissible on שמיטה? Shmita? מאי
שנא שביעית דשרי? Mai Shna Shvis Desharei? Why can you do this
deworming on שמיטה, Shmita, and מאי שנא מועד דאסור, Mai Shna Moed
D'Assur, not on חול המועד? Chol HaMoed? So מי דמי? Mi Dami?
You can't compare them. שביעית מלאכה אסר רחמנא טירחא שרי. Shviis Melacha
Assar Rachmana Tircha Sharei. שביעית Shvis the Torah only forbade מלאכה, Melacha,
things like planting and seeding. Now מלאכה Melacha doesn't mean the thirty-nine
מלאכות Melachos of שבת, Shabbos, but you know, classic type of agricultural
activities. This deworming isn't a plowing, planting, watering, you know, hoeing.
Deworming, it's effort, but it's not a מלאכה. Melacha. מועד אפילו טירחא
נמי אסור. Moed Afilu Tircha Nami Assur. On חול המועד, Chol HaMoed,
even overexertion is a problem. Now תוספות of course deals with the
part that if the tree is going to get rotted and lost
and destroyed, you know, there's ideas about הפסד Hefsed on חול המועד
Chol HaMoed and הפסד מרובה Hefsed Merubeh and sometimes we allow טירחא.
Tircha. So, but as a start-off position, it's not it's not just
about מלאכה, Melacha, it's even things of effort. So that explains that
difference if that was what was bothering you. Maybe there's something else
bothering you. Let's keep on going. ואלא זיהום אגוזים קקשיא ליה. Ve'ella
Zium Aguzim KaKasha Le.
So you want to know what is the... so that explains the
difference between שמיטה Shmita and חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. Maybe what's bothering
you though is the difference between why you're allowed to attach bark
and you're not allowed to prune. מאי שנא Mai Shna on שמיטה,
Shmita, מאי שנא זיהום דשרי, Mai Shna Zium Desharei, why are you
allowed to attach bark, ומאי שנא גיזום דאסור, U'mai Shna Gizum De'Assur,
why are you not allowed to prune? So that's an obvious answer.
מי דמי? Mi Dami? Who can compare them? זיהום אוקמי אילנא. Zium
Ukme Ilana. זיהום Zium
is to, you know, have the tree, support the tree, meaning prevent
it from rotting, prevent it from getting destroyed. Okay, it's weak, it
needs strengthening. ושרי, VeSharei, it's permissible because you're protecting it. גיזום, Gizum,
but pruning, אברויי אילנא, Avruei Ilana, it's to make it better. It's
to make it grow more. It's not to prevent it from being
destroyed. So on שמיטה Shmita you're not allowed to do things that,
you know, support growth, that encourage growth. You're allowed to do things
to protect it. So that's why one is שרי Sharei and the
other is אסור. Assur. ואלא זיהום אזיהום קקשיא ליה. Ve'ella Zium A'Zium
KaKasha Le.
Okay, here maybe is what was bothering you, the difference about whether
the act of זיהום Zium itself of this thing about like the
attaching of the bark is itself permissible or forbidden on שמיטה. Shmita.
Because our משנה Mishnah says it's permissible,
דקתני מזהמין ומזפתים בשביעית. DeKtani Mazhimin U'Mezaftin B'Shviis. I mean, our ברייתא
that was taught says it's permissible on שמיטה. Shmita. And we explained
why. It's not a מלאכה. Melacha. It's only effort. It's only there
to protect the tree. That's why it's permissible. ורמינהי,
but I'll ask you on this. Okay, we've got a משנה: Mishnah
מזהמין את הנטיעות וכורכין אותן, Mazhimin Et HaNetiot VeKorkhin Otan,
you can go ahead and do this זיהום, Zium, whatever it is,
again, this attaching of bark to these young saplings and wrap around
them, you know, to protect them. וקוטמין אותן VeKotmin Otan and you
can like a little, you know, cut off twigs. ועושין להן בתים
VeOsin Lahen Batim and you can make little like, you know, little
protective little, you know, boxes around them. ומשקין אותן U'Mashkin Otan and
you can water them עד ראש השנה, Ad Rosh Hashana, until the
actual day of שמיטה Shmita itself. עד ראש השנה אין בשביעית לא.
Ad Rosh Hashana In B'Shviis Lo. Until the day of ראש השנה
Rosh Hashana yes, בשביעית B'Shviis no, you can't do זיהום Zium of
these saplings on שמיטה. Shmita. So your ברייתא says you can do
זיהום, Zium, it's only to protect the tree, it's not a מלאכה,
Melacha, but this משנה Mishnah says what? Maintenance. Maintenance, right. But this
משנה mishna says you can't do זיהום Zium on שמיטה Shmita itself.
So the גמרא says why does that have to bother you? ודילמא
כדרב עוקבא בר חמא. U'Dilma KiDeRav Ukva Bar Chama. Maybe this follows
the ruling of רב עוקבא בר חמא. Rav Ukva Bar Chama. דאמר
רב עוקבא בר חמא תרי קשקושי הוו. De'Amar Rav Ukva Bar Chama
Tre Kishkushe Havei. There are two types of, you know, קשקוש Kishkush
which is some other type of a thing. רש״י says it's like
the digging of the dirt under the olive trees. חד לאברויי אילנא,
Chad
L'Avruei
Ilana, one certain type of way it's done... what? קש. Kash. Okay.
קש. Kash. Straw. Straw maybe, I don't know. I thought it was
קשקושי. Kishkushe. I don't know. It's קשקושי. Kishkushe. I'm not sure. How
did they how did they vowelize it? קשקוש Kishkush or קשקוש? Kashkush?
Anybody have the vowels? Okay, you'll tell me. Oh, it's קשקושי Kishkushe
with a שין. Shin. Okay. Okay, תרי קשקושי הוו. Tre Kishkushe Havei.
There are two types of קשקוש. Kishkush. חד לאברויי אילנא, Chad L'Avruei
Ilana, one is to encourage the growth, strengthen the tree, ואסור, VeAssur,
and that's forbidden. וחד לסתומי פילי, VeChad L'Satumme Pili, one is just
to fill in the holes, ושרי, VeSharei, and it's to maintenance and
protecting and that's permissible. קשקושי. Kishkushe. Okay fine. הכא נמי תרי זיהומי
הוו. Hacha Nami Tre Ziumme Havei. So we could say the same
thing. There are two types of this attaching of bark. חד לאוקמי
אילנא ושרי, Chad L'Ukme Ilana VeSharei, the one that the ברייתא says
you're allowed to do on שמיטה Shmita is to protect the tree.
וחד לאברויי אילנא ואסור, VeChad L'Avruei Ilana VeAssur, and the one that
the משנה teaches that's forbidden is when it's to encourage growth and
make it, you know, and make it grow more. Okay, so we
explained everything. מועד Moed is more forbidden because it's טירחא. Tircha. These
things, the things that are for maintenance are permissible, the things that
are to encourage growth are forbidden. Everything works. ואלא סיכה סיכה קקשיא
ליה. Ve'ella Sichasikha KaKasha Le. Whether you're allowed to appoint... place the
oil on it. דקתני DeKtani our משנה says: סכין שמן לגזום בין
במועד בין בשביעית. Sakhin Shemen LaGazum Bein B'Moed Bein B'Shviis. You're allowed
to put oil on the pruned parts, whether on מועד Moed or
on שביעית. Shviis. oil on the cut spot, whether it's שמיטה Shmita
or חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. Presumably that's more to protect it. ורמינהו,
Varminhu, but I'll ask you on this. We've got a משנה that
says סכין את הפגין, Sachin et hapagin, that you can go ahead
and rub oil on these unripe fruit. ומנקבין ומפטמין אותן, U'menakvin u'mefatmin
otan, and you could put holes in them and maybe even fatten
them, pour oil into the holes, עד ראש השנה Ad Rosh Hashana
of שמיטה. Shmita. עד ראש השנה, Ad Rosh Hashana, yes; בשביעית, b'shvi'it,
no. So again, oil there is forbidden on שמיטה, Shmita, here it's
permissible. Of course, the difference is one is putting oil on fruit
and the other is putting it on a cut branch. So the
גמרא says מי דמי? Mi dami? Who can compare it? הכא אוקמי
אילנא ושרי. Hacha ukmei ilana v'shari. When it's putting it on the
cut branch, it's just to prevent that area, exposed area, from being
damaged. It's to protect it and it's permissible. התם פטומי פירות, Hatam
pitumei peirot, there it's to fatten the fruit, to actually make it
grow more, ואסור, v'asur, and it's forbidden. Okay, so everything makes sense.
What's bothering you? אמר ליה רב סמא בריה דרב אשי לרבינא, Amar
leh Rav Sama bereh deRav Ashi leRavina, בר ירמיה, סיכא דמועד אזימא
דמועד קשיא ליה. Sicha de'moed azima de'moed kashya leh. Here's what bothered
him: within the ברייתא itself, why do we allow the oil on
the cut branch on חול המועד Chol HaMoed but we don't allow
the attaching of the bark? Since they both seem to be about
protecting the tree, why is one forbidden and one permissible? That's actually
a good question. Okay, מכדי האי אוקמי והאי אוקמי. Michdi hai ukmei
v'hai ukmei. You just got through saying that both of these are
to protect the tree and that's why they're allowed on שמיטה. Shmita.
So מאי שנא האי דשרי ומאי שנא האי דאסור? mai shena hai
deshari u'mai shena hai de'asur? So why is the anointing of the
putting of the oil permissible and the putting of the bark forbidden?
Now, obviously there could be some answer about what is the degree
of risk of loss for one or the other, what is the
degree of effort, what's the ratio of the two? But at least
that's the question. Okay, clearly they're both there to protect the tree
and one's forbidden and one's permissible. All right, so היינו דקאמר ליה
ליכא נגר
ולא בר נגר דיפרקינה.
hainu d'ka'amar leh
leka nagar v'lo bar nagar de'ifarkina. That's why you say we don't
have a carpenter or son of a carpenter to explain it. Now,
of course, there could be an answer, but based on the particulars,
but at least on the face of it there's not a clear
rule. Is stuff to protect the tree, is that permissible or not
permissible on חול המועד? Chol HaMoed? All right, so that was a
nice big digression. Back to our basic, back to our case. That
went pretty quickly. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב. Amar Rav Yehuda amar
Rav. Now, back to, we were just discussing תקרובת and if something
is not done as כעין פנים like it was worshipped, like worship
is done, either based on the object or the process, then the
object does not become forbidden as תקרובת עבודה זרה. tikrovat avoda zara.
Now the גמרא is going to get into a whole fascinating discussion
of how much certain acts have to match how we define things.
Okay, let's take a look. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav
Yehuda amar Rav, עבודת כוכבים שעובדין אותה במקל. avodat kochavim she'ovdin otah
b'makkel. You have an עבודה avoda, זרה that a classic act of
worship is done with a stick. רש"י Rashi says let's say you
would twirl a baton in front of it. Okay, that would be
what you would normally do. But now you're not twirling the baton.
What you went ahead and did was, שעובדין אותה במקל, she'ovdin otah
b'makkel, שבר מקל בפניה חייב. shavar makkel befaneyha chayav. Rather than twirl
the baton, you took the baton and you broke it. That's an
act of עבודה זרה. Now we're not talking about whether the baton
is forbidden or not, is it a תקרובת? Maybe we can get
back to that. Right now our focus is on was this an
act of עבודה זרה? So if you broke the stick you're חייב.
chayav. זרק מקל בפניה פטור. Zarak makkel befaneyha patur. If you threw
it you're exempt. Now why is this? So what we have to
do is remind ourselves of two basic categories from the גמרא in
סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. One is anything that is a classic עבודה in the
בית המקדש, even if it's not normally the way something is worshipped,
is considered עבודה זרה and you're חייב. chayav. Even if the only
way מרקוליס is worshipped is by throwing stones, if you went and
you took an animal and you slaughtered it in front of the
מרקוליס, you'd be חייב. chayav. If you took the blood from the
animal and you threw it on the מרקוליס, you'd be חייב. chayav.
If you burnt incense in front of the מרקוליס, you'd be חייב.
chayav. The things that are the classic ways of doing עבודה in
the בית המקדש is considered an act of עבודה and you're חייב
chayav even if it's not normal. Then there is how do the
non-Jews actually do the worship. If you threw a stone at מרקוליס
you're also חייב. chayav. But if you didn't do any of those
things, you didn't do שחיטה shechita or זריקת הדם, zrikat hadam, you
didn't throw stones, you did some other, you did a Zeus worship
in front of מרקוליס, you'd be פטור. patur. All right, so what's
the issue here of the stick? So the way רש"י Rashi explains
the issue of the stick, it's like by breaking a stick that's
sort of like שחיטה. shechita. But you didn't do שחיטה shechita on
an animal. You did שחיטה shechita on a stick. Okay, now the
normal way they worshipped it is not by breaking the stick. The
normal way they worshipped it is by spinning the stick like a
baton. So you're not חייב chayav for doing the normal way of
worship. Are you חייב chayav for doing the classic way of worship
of שחיטה, shechita, זריקת הדם zrikat hadam etc.? So the answer here
according to this is yes, we can get you from that category
by saying even though you didn't use an animal and even though
you didn't use blood, since they use a stick in their worship,
the stick takes the place of the animal. And therefore, it's like
you did שחיטה shechita on an animal. So if you didn't take
a stick, if you took I don't know, a vase and you
broke it, okay, that's neither category. But once they use the stick
in their worship, that makes the stick the object that's offered and
then you put it, plug it into the category of the classic
four and if you do a שחיטה shechita on the stick, you're
חייב. chayav. Or burn it, like as if you were to burn
something on the altar, exactly. Okay, so that's what he says. So
that's a pretty big חידוש. chiddush. Okay, שבר מקל לפניו חייב זרק
מקל לפניו פטור. shavar makkel lefanav chayav, zarak makkel lefanav patur. אמר
ליה אביי לרבא, Amar lei Abaye le-Rava, אביי Abaye said to רבא,
מאי שנא שבר? Mai shna shavar? Why is, once you've established that
the stick is like the animal, why are you חייב chayav for
the stick? Because it's like slaughtering. So זרק נמי הוי ליה כעין
זריקה. zarak nami havei lei k'ein zrika. So throwing the stick should
be like throwing the blood. אמר ליה, Amar lei, no, בעינא זריקה
משתברת וליכא. be'ina zrika mishtaberet ve-leika. No, when you throw blood, the
blood splatters. When you throw a stick, it just falls down. Okay,
so it's not close enough, right? שחיטה shechita actually cuts into something
and breaks it, that's close enough. But it's not throwing an object
like throwing a ball, catch. Okay, the throwing of blood is a
throwing that leads things to splatter and he says משתברת, mishtaberet, like
to break into pieces. So it's not similar enough. Of course, you
know, it's a little bit hard trying to fit new objects in
and figure out exactly what makes it. But that's the idea. If
we identify the object, if we can plug it into the category
and the act is similar enough, you'll be חייב. chayav. If he
threw sand? If he threw sand. If sand was an object they
used in the worship. So if they did something with sand, they
made sandcastles and that was their way of doing עבודה, and you
took the sand and you threw it, then you'd be חייב, chayav,
right. You have to though get the object into the discussion. Okay,
so we will pick up with this tomorrow to see about how
this all plays out. All right. Does it make a difference if
the stick is like green or dry because...